start with rational numbers A over B
less than or equal to C over D we can
represent the rational number A over B
as the slope of the hypotenuse of a
right triangle with side lengths A and B
and we can represent C over d as the
slope of the hypotenuse of a right
triangle with legs of length C and D by
assumption the latter triangle has a
steeper hypotenuse if we shift the
triangle so their vertices connect like
this we can fit them inside of a larger
right triangle with sides of length B
plus d and a plus c by investigating the
slopes of the hypotenuses in this
diagram we see that A over B is less
than or equal to the quantity a + C / B
+ D and that's less than or equal to C
over D the fraction in the middle of
this inequality a plus c over B + D is
known as the mediant of the two
fractions so we can define an operation
where we combine A over B and C over D
to produce a plus c over B plus d and
this is called the median operation due
to this terminology the inequality we
proved is sometimes called the mediant
inequality